In the last video, we ran a quadistatic muscle simulation with collision and muscle contraction.
지난 영상에서는 충돌과 근수축이 포함된 준정적(quasi‑static) 근육 시뮬레이션을 실행했습니다.
In this video, we'll add the fat layer on top of the muscles instead of a coupled muscle and fat simulation.
이번 영상에서는 근육과 지방을 결합해 돌리는 대신, 근육 위에 지방층을 얹는 방식으로 진행하겠습니다.
Let's first take a look at the fat static mesh.
먼저 지방용 스태틱 메쉬를 확인해 보죠.
Over here, let's open that. You can see the vertex count here, the number of vertices here, is really high.
여기서 열어보면, 여기 버텍스 수, 즉 정점 개수가 상당히 많다는 걸 볼 수 있습니다.
That means when you're running a TetWild or CreateTeproHeader node on this static mesh converted to collection,
이는 이 스태틱 메쉬를 컬렉션으로 변환한 뒤 TetWild 또는 CreateTeproHeader 노드를 실행하면,
the runtime will be really, really high. So let's go ahead and downsample the static mesh here.
실행 시간이 아주 아주 오래 걸린다는 뜻입니다. 그래서 여기서는 스태틱 메쉬를 다운샘플 하겠습니다.
So right-click and then duplicate the static mesh here.
우클릭해서 이 스태틱 메쉬를 복제하세요.
I'm going to call this one the downsample.
이 복제본 이름은 downsample로 하겠습니다.
And then you can drag this one into the environment and then reset the location so that it's the best location.
그런 다음 이걸 월드에 끌어다 놓고, 위치를 리셋해서 보기 좋은 위치로 맞춰줍니다.
Press F to zoom in onto the static mesh here.
F 키를 눌러 이 스태틱 메쉬로 줌인하세요.
Over here, the selection mode, let's go ahead and change that to the modeling mode.
여기 선택 모드를 모델링 모드로 바꿉시다.
And now we can go to mesh and then simplify.
이제 Mesh 메뉴에서 Simplify로 들어갑니다.
This will open up the Simplification tool.
그러면 Simplification 도구가 열립니다.
For simplifier type, instead of QEM, let's use existing positions.
Simplifier Type은 QEM 대신 Existing Positions를 사용하겠습니다.
We're trying our best to preserve the shape of our static mesh.
스태틱 메쉬의 형상을 최대한 보존하려고 합니다.
For talking mode, let's use vertex count.
타깃 모드는 Vertex Count를 쓰겠습니다.
Let's set our ideal vertex count to be 30,000.
목표 버텍스 수는 30,000으로 설정합시다.
For this example, we need to check this discard attribute for simplification to work.
이 예제에서는 Simplification이 동작하려면 Discard Attributes 옵션을 체크해야 합니다.
Now you can see we've got a different topology.
이제 보면 토폴로지가 달라졌습니다.
And this one is much worse than before.
그리고 이전보다 훨씬 안 좋아졌네요.
Hit accept to accept this result.
Accept를 눌러 이 결과를 적용합니다.
And make sure you save this new static mesh.
그리고 새 스태틱 메쉬를 꼭 저장하세요.
Now we can go to the tetrahedral meshes folder and then work on the tetrahedral mesh for the fat layer.
이제 사면체 메쉬 폴더로 가서 지방층용 사면체 메쉬 작업을 하겠습니다.
Same thing as the muscles, let's create a new flesh asset.
근육 때와 동일하게 새로운 Flesh 에셋을 만듭니다.
I'm going to call this one the fat tetrahedral mesh.
이름은 fat tetrahedral mesh로 하겠습니다.
Flesh asset.
Flesh 에셋입니다.
Create a new dataflow asset.
새 데이터플로우 에셋을 만듭니다.
The first node we're going to create is the static mesh.
첫 번째로 만들 노드는 Static Mesh입니다.
Let's bring in the static mesh we just created.
방금 만든 스태틱 메쉬를 가져오죠.
There is our downsampled static mesh.
다운샘플된 스태틱 메쉬가 여기 있습니다.
We can convert the static mesh to a collection using the static mesh to a collection node.
StaticMeshToCollection 노드를 사용해 스태틱 메쉬를 컬렉션으로 변환할 수 있습니다.
Note that over here you have choices of split components of the static mesh.
여기에는 스태틱 메쉬의 컴포넌트를 분리(split)할지 선택하는 옵션이 있습니다.
That means if you have...
즉, 만약에 …
For example, if your muscles were a static mesh, then you want to split components and then split muscles into different geometries.
예를 들어 근육이 하나의 스태틱 메쉬라면, 컴포넌트를 분리해서 근육을 여러 지오메트리로 나누고 싶을 겁니다.
In this case, it doesn't really matter.
이번 경우엔 크게 상관없습니다.
So we just leave that as off.
그래서 Off로 두겠습니다.
Connect that static mesh here.
여기 스태틱 메쉬를 연결하세요.
This will convert our fat layer into a collection.
그러면 지방층이 컬렉션으로 변환됩니다.
So over here in the construction viewport, you can press F to zoom in onto the fat layer.
구성 뷰포트에서 F를 눌러 지방층으로 줌인할 수 있습니다.
There is the static mesh.
스태틱 메쉬가 보이죠.
Next, let's create a tetrahedral mesh using the create tetrahedral node.
다음으로 Create Tetrahedral 노드로 사면체 메쉬를 생성합시다.
For the parameters, you can go back to the first video where I'll explain the parameters in a while here.
파라미터는 1편에서 자세히 설명했으니 곧 다시 요약하겠습니다.
Over here, let's use the optimal parameters I found.
여기서는 제가 찾아둔 최적 파라미터를 쓰겠습니다.
In this case, you actually want to use a lower Fs for L value because this set mesh is really thin.
이 경우 메쉬가 매우 얇기 때문에 Fs for L 값을 더 낮게 쓰는 게 좋습니다.
And then you want the surface of the tetrahedral mesh to track that closely.
그리고 사면체 메쉬의 표면이 원래 표면을 가깝게 따라가도록 해야 합니다.
So that doesn't leave any holes in your tetrahedral mesh.
그래야 사면체 메쉬에 구멍이 생기지 않습니다.
Especially in thin regions.
특히 얇은 부분에서요.
So let's go ahead and change that to be 0.0001.
그래서 값을 0.0001로 낮추겠습니다.
So one order of magnitude down.
한 자릿수(오더) 더 낮춘 셈이죠.
Same thing, check that course in box.
마찬가지로 Coarsen 박스를 체크합니다.
In this case, we'll not have any collection here because we don't need a transform attribute anymore.
이번에는 Transform Attribute가 더 이상 필요 없으므로 컬렉션 입력은 비워둡니다.
We already have the transform attributes stored in the muscles.
변환(트랜스폼) 속성은 이미 근육 쪽에 저장되어 있습니다.
And eventually we'll append this fat tetrahedral mesh onto the muscles so that they share the same transform attributes.
결국 이 지방 사면체 메쉬를 근육에 append 해서 같은 트랜스폼 속성을 공유하게 만들 겁니다.
So the only thing we need to do is collect the collection to the source collection.
그래서 여기서는 Source Collection에 컬렉션만 연결하면 됩니다.
And now the node is real frozen, it starts to evaluate the node.
노드가 얼어붙어 보이지만, 평가가 시작된 것입니다.
Alright, so we waited about 15 minutes for this node to finish the evaluation.
이 노드가 평가를 끝낼 때까지 약 15분 기다렸습니다.
Let's go ahead and check this tetrahedral mesh that's created from the stack mesh of the fat layer.
이제 지방층의 스태틱 메쉬로부터 생성된 사면체 메쉬를 확인해 보죠.
We go to vertices and check the vertex count there.
Vertices 탭으로 가서 버텍스 수를 봅니다.
52,000 vertices.
52,000 버텍스입니다.
The last node we'll create is the terminal node.
마지막으로 Terminal 노드를 만듭니다.
FleshAssetTerminal.
FleshAssetTerminal 입니다.
Now we can save the tetrahedral mesh collection into our flesh asset here.
이제 이 사면체 메쉬 컬렉션을 Flesh 에셋에 저장할 수 있습니다.
Let's go ahead and save the full flesh asset.
전체 Flesh 에셋을 저장합시다.
Then we're gonna do the same thing as we did for the muscles.
그리고 근육에서 했던 것과 같은 작업을 반복하겠습니다.
We're gonna start a new flesh asset for the setup.
셋업용으로 새로운 Flesh 에셋을 시작합니다.
Let's go into the flesh asset folder.
Flesh 에셋 폴더로 갑시다.
Create a new flesh asset.
새 Flesh 에셋을 만듭니다.
I can call this one Muscle Setup. Create a new dinner flow asset.
이름은 Muscle Setup. 새 데이터플로우 에셋도 만듭니다.
And now the first node is of course importing the Muscle Flesh Asset as well as the Fat Flesh Asset.
첫 노드는 당연히 Muscle Flesh Asset과 Fat Flesh Asset을 가져오는 것입니다.
So let's go ahead and grab the Muscle Setup Flesh Asset that contains our Muscle Setup.
그래서 Muscle Setup이 들어 있는 Muscle Setup Flesh Asset을 가져오겠습니다.
Call this one the Muscle Asset.
이 노드 이름은 Muscle Asset으로 하죠.
We also need another one to import the tetrakeletal metric of the fat layer that we just created.
방금 만든 지방층의 사면체 메쉬를 가져오는 노드도 하나 더 필요합니다.
In this case, it's a Fat Tetrakeletal metric Flesh Asset.
여기서는 Fat tetrahedral mesh Flesh Asset입니다.
At this point, we need to set some mass and stiffness properties on the fat layer,
이제 지방층에는 아직 질량과 강성(stiffness) 속성을 설정하지 않았으니,
as we haven't done that.
아직 설정을 안 했기 때문이죠.
So creating SetFleshDefault properties.
그래서 SetFleshDefault Properties를 만듭니다.
For this node, we'll set Density to be 100 and Vertex Stiffness to be 10,000.
여기서 Density는 100, Vertex Stiffness는 10,000으로 설정합니다.
Note that the Density and Vertex Stiffness are both one order of magnitude lower than the one from Muscles,
이 값들은 근육에서 썼던 값보다 각각 한 자릿수(오더) 낮습니다.
because we want the deformation of the Muscles to dominate the fat layer so that we're able to see the muscle contractions.
그 이유는 근육의 변형이 지방층보다 지배적이어서 근수축이 눈에 띄게 보이도록 하기 위함입니다.
If they're approximately the same, say the Vertex Stiffness is the same as the one we use for Muscles,
만약 두 값이 비슷하다면, 예를 들어 Vertex Stiffness가 근육과 같다면,
then the elasticity will kill the Muscle deformation because we have elasticity in the fat layer.
지방층의 탄성 때문에 근육 변형이 사라져 보이게 됩니다.
Now let's create an append node.
이제 Append 노드를 만듭시다.
We're going to use append the tetrakeletal collection.
Append Tetrahedral Collection을 사용하겠습니다.
This will take two collections, Collection 1 and Collection 2.
이 노드는 Collection 1과 Collection 2, 두 컬렉션을 입력으로 받습니다.
This will put Collection 2 attributes to the front and then Collection 1 attributes to the end.
Collection 2의 속성이 앞쪽에, Collection 1의 속성이 뒤쪽에 붙습니다.
Let's go ahead and connect Muscles here and also the fat layer here.
근육을 여기, 지방층을 여기 연결합시다.
You can see now everything is being appended together.
이제 모두가 하나로 합쳐진 걸 볼 수 있습니다.
The number of vertices there.
버텍스 수도 확인되네요.
When we append collections, attribute values that depend on the size of other groups,
컬렉션을 Append 할 때, 다른 그룹의 크기에 의존하는 속성 값들은
For example, attributes that depend on from size of vertices, or size of geometry , those will
자동으로 갱신됩니다. 예를 들어 버텍스 수나 지오메트리 수에 의존하는 속성들이요.
get updated automatically. So one example is, if it goes to muscle activation here, you can see the
예시로 Muscle Activation을 보면,
Geometry group index is 28 and 58. That's dependent on the geometry group. But prior to the collection,
Geometry Group Index가 28과 58입니다. 이 값은 지오메트리 그룹에 의존합니다. 그런데 Append 전,
if you go to just the muscle assets, and muscle activation now these are 27 and 57, the reason
근육 에셋만 볼 때 Muscle Activation은 27과 57이었습니다. 그 이유는
is that we have the fat layer here that bumps the Geometry group up by one. Now we can click this node
지방층이 하나 추가되면서 Geometry Group이 하나씩 밀렸기 때문입니다. 이제 이 노드를
here and press F, so that we can see the coupled collection here, we can see it contains both
선택하고 F를 누르면, 결합된 컬렉션이 보이고
muscles and the fat layer. So let's create some weak constraints or positioned target constraints
근육과 지방층이 모두 포함된 걸 확인할 수 있습니다. 이제 약한 제약(weak constraints), 즉 Position Target 제약을 조금 만들겠습니다.
We can do this through the set vertex triangle position target binding.
Set Vertex/Triangle Position Target Binding 노드를 사용하면 됩니다.
By default, this node creates springs between every pair of closed-by connected geometries. So in this case, it will create springs between muscles, muscles, and muscle muscles, and fat.
기본적으로 이 노드는 모든 쌍 사이에 스프링을 만듭니다. 근육–근육, 근육–지방, 지방–지방처럼요.
Especially, it will create springs between the outer surface of the fat layer and the muscles, because sometimes the fat layer is thin and they're getting too close.
특히 바깥 표면끼리도 스프링을 만드는데, 지방층이 얇아 가까워지는 경우가 있어 문제가 됩니다.
So we want to avoid that by specifying only the inner side of the fat layer to get weak constraints bound to the muscles.
그래서 지방층의 안쪽 면만 근육에 약한 제약으로 바인딩되도록 지정하겠습니다.
We can do this through painting and then eventually specifying a vertex selection over here.
페인팅을 통해 버텍스 선택을 만들어서 그렇게 설정할 수 있습니다.
So let's go ahead and get the StagMesh to Collection node.
StaticMeshToCollection 노드를 하나 더 가져옵시다.
We can set the StagMesh to be our FatLayer.
Static Mesh는 FatLayer로 설정합니다.
Remember we used the down-sampled one.
다운샘플된 것을 썼다는 걸 기억하세요.
Then we can paint on the StagMesh and then transfer the Attributes onto the Tetriqueter mesh.
이제 이 스태틱 메쉬 위에 페인팅하고, 그 Attribute를 사면체 메쉬로 전송(Transfer)합니다.
So let's go ahead and create an AddWeekMap.
AddWeightMap을 만들어 줍니다.
That will create an AddScalarMurfixProperty node.
그러면 AddScalar…Property 노드가 생성됩니다.
And then we can select the FatLayer and start painting on that.
그런 다음 FatLayer를 선택하고 페인팅을 시작합니다.
In this case we want to use the Brush Tool, set Strength to be 1,
이때 Brush 툴을 쓰고 Strength는 1로,
and then set VisibilityFilter to be un-occluded, because we don't want to paint anything on the inner side.
Visibility Filter는 Un-occluded로 설정합니다. 안쪽 면에는 칠하고 싶지 않기 때문입니다.
The strategy is we're going to paint on the outer side of the fat layer, and then revert the selection so that we have a painting of the inner layer.
전략은 바깥쪽 면을 먼저 칠한 다음, 선택을 반전해서 안쪽 층에만 칠한 결과를 얻는 것입니다.
Let's go ahead and paint the outer surface.
그럼 바깥 표면을 칠해봅시다.
Sometimes you see that these triangles are missing.
가끔 삼각형 일부가 빠져 보일 수 있습니다.
That means you need to adjust to a different angle and then you can grab those.
그럴 땐 시점을 조금 바꿔 잡으면 선택할 수 있습니다.
Now I've spent a few minutes to perfect my painting on the outer surface.
저는 바깥 표면을 몇 분 더 다듬었습니다.
After that, we can invert the painting here by selecting this Invert Current Surface button.
그런 뒤 Invert Current Surface 버튼을 눌러 페인팅을 반전합니다.
That will basically invert the painting attributes on the surface.
이렇게 하면 표면의 페인팅 속성이 반전됩니다.
Note that this Invert Current button will invert everything on all vertices, meaning that any internal vertices will also get the attributes inverted.
주의할 점은 Invert Current 버튼이 모든 것을 반전시켜 내부 버텍스까지 바뀔 수 있다는 겁니다.
In this case, we only want to invert the surface.
이번에는 표면만 반전해야 합니다.
So make sure you select this button, click Accept, and then make sure we assign a name for this.
그러니 이 버튼을 선택하고 Accept를 누른 다음, 이름을 꼭 지정하세요.
Let's call this one the Inner Fat.
이름은 Inner Fat으로 하겠습니다.
Now we can transfer onto the fat layer.
이제 이걸 지방층으로 전송(Transfer)할 수 있습니다.
So let's go ahead and then drag this out and create a Transfer Vertex Attribute node.
드래그해서 Transfer Vertex Attribute 노드를 만듭니다.
Then for From Collection, let's connect that as well as the Attribute Key.
From Collection과 Attribute Key를 각각 연결하세요.
I can replace the Collection here.
여기 컬렉션 입력을 교체할 수 있습니다.
Now this Combined Collection should also contain the Inner Fat Attribute I just created.
이제 Combined Collection에도 방금 만든 Inner Fat 속성이 들어 있을 겁니다.
So let's grab the Vertex Selection from this Attribute.
이 Attribute에서 Vertex Selection을 뽑아오죠.
The node that we'll use is Collection Select by Attribute.
사용할 노드는 Collection Select by Attribute입니다.
Let's go ahead and connect that Collection.
컬렉션을 연결합니다.
Also connect the Attribute Key here.
Attribute Key도 연결합니다.
And over here, because we have Group and Attribute connected, we can simply ignore these.
Group과 Attribute를 이미 연결했으므로, 이 옵션들은 무시해도 됩니다.
For operation, we're selecting vertices based on this operation.
Operation은 이 조건에 맞는 버텍스를 선택하는 방식입니다.
So let's set that to be greater than, because we're selecting anything that's 1, then set the value to be 0.5.
값이 1인 것들을 뽑을 것이므로 Greater Than(>)으로 두고, 임계값을 0.5로 둡니다.
And the logic is that any vertex that has that attribute greater than 0.5 will be selected.
즉 해당 Attribute가 0.5보다 큰 버텍스가 선택됩니다.
And now that will return a vertex selection of the Inner Fat node.
이렇게 해서 Inner Fat에 대한 버텍스 선택이 반환됩니다.
Let's connect that, and also connect Collection here.
그 선택을 연결하고, 컬렉션도 연결합니다.
Before that, let's go ahead and adjust the parameter of the Target Stiffuse here and set that to be 10.
그 전에 Target Stiffness 파라미터를 10으로 조정합시다.
And then the vertex radius ratio to be 0.004, and connect Collection there.
Vertex Radius Ratio는 0.004로 하고, 컬렉션을 연결합니다.
Now we'll build some weak constraints between the Inner Fat and the Muscles.
이제 Inner Fat과 근육 사이에 약한 제약들을 만들겠습니다.
We can visualize the results again by calling this Visualized Position Target node.
Visualize Position Target 노드를 호출해서 결과를 시각화할 수 있습니다.
We have that rendered, then we can see all the weak constraints that's on this Collection, including the Muscle and Muscle Constraints, really.
렌더링되면 컬렉션 전반의 약한 제약들—근육–근육 제약까지—을 볼 수 있습니다.
You see these smaller ones, these are the ones between the Inner Fat and the Muscles.
그중 작은 것들이 Inner Fat과 근육 사이의 제약입니다.
This is a way to check whether you're getting a sufficient amount of weak constraints.
충분한 양의 약한 제약이 생성됐는지 확인하는 방법입니다.
Now that we have weak constraints between the Muscles and the Fat layer, we really don't have any muscles along the spine or around the clavicle.
근육과 지방 사이에 약한 제약을 만들었지만, 척추나 쇄골 주변에는 근육이 없습니다.
So let's go ahead and bring in the bones for visualization.
그래서 시각화를 위해 뼈대를 불러오겠습니다.
You can set the sculpt mesh to be the bones, and have that, and also the Muscles selected, the Muscle and Fat.
Skeletal Mesh를 Bones로 설정하고, 근육과 지방도 함께 선택해 표시합니다.
If you go to the Muscle here, here, and then having the bones also visualize here, you can actually copy and paste the note.
근육 쪽으로 가서 뼈 표시도 함께 보이게 한 뒤, 노드를 복사해서 붙여넣을 수도 있습니다.
Let's go ahead and copy and paste, Ctrl-C and Ctrl-V. You can see the bones here.
Ctrl-C, Ctrl-V로 복붙하면 뼈가 보입니다.
You can see there are no muscles around the clavicle and also along the spine here.
보시다시피 쇄골 주변과 척추를 따라 근육이 없습니다.
And we're going to need some constraints between the Fat layer and the bones on those reasons, because we don't have anything else to drive the Fat layer.
따라서 지방층을 구동할 다른 것이 없으므로, 이 구간들에는 추가 제약이 필요합니다.
So let's go ahead and create some Kinematic constraints.
그러니 Kinematic 제약을 몇 개 만들겠습니다.
Let's use Set Flesh Bone Position Target Binding. Again, set this one to Kinematic.
Set Flesh Bone Position Target Binding을 사용하고, 모드는 다시 Kinematic으로 둡니다.
Then for Radius Ratio, it's set to be 0.002. And then for Scalzo Mesh, let's give that bone Scalzo Mesh.
Radius Ratio는 0.002로 설정하고, Skeletal Mesh는 해당 뼈의 Skeletal Mesh를 지정합니다.
Let's connect that.
그것들을 연결하세요.
Now we can also visualize Kinematic Faces.
이제 Kinematic Faces도 시각화할 수 있습니다.
Let's go ahead and check if we have anything on the clavicle.
쇄골 부위에 설정된 게 있는지 확인해 봅시다.
You can see now these are the Kinematic Faces along the clavicle and also along the ribcage, or the sternum.
쇄골을 따라, 그리고 흉곽(흉골) 주변에 Kinematic Faces가 있는 게 보일 겁니다.
Also some along the spine, which is good. That provides extra constraints.
척추를 따라 있는 것도 보이는데, 좋은 징후입니다. 추가 제약을 제공합니다.
We also have some around the elbow, which is really good. We don't have much muscles there.
팔꿈치 주변도 조금 있는데, 거긴 근육이 많지 않으니 아주 좋습니다.
And finally, let's save this into a terminal. It's called the Flesh Asset Terminal node.
마지막으로 Flesh Asset Terminal 노드로 저장합시다.
And then save the collection into the Flesh Asset.
그리고 컬렉션을 Flesh 에셋에 저장합니다.
Ctrl-S, we can save the progress of setup here.
Ctrl+S로 현재 셋업 진행 상황을 저장할 수 있습니다.
As a recap, we created a coupled Flesh Asset of both the Muscles and the Fat layer.
요약하면, 근육과 지방층이 결합된 Flesh 에셋을 만들었습니다.
We set up some Kinematic and also weak constraints on the Fat layer.
그리고 지방층에는 Kinematic 제약과 Weak 제약을 일부 설정했습니다.
In the next video, we'll run a quality-side simulation on the coupled asset.
다음 영상에서는 결합 에셋에 대해 준정적(quasi‑static) 시뮬레이션을 실행하겠습니다.